so this is another auna talk some ex
exod this talk is called understanding
Dua there is a difficulty in practice
but in anything we undertake we have to
pass through difficulty to reach ease in
dummer practice we be we begin with the
truth of Dua the pervasive
unsatisfactoriness of existence but as
soon as we experience this we lose heart
we don't want to look at
it Dua is rarely the truth but when but
we want to get around it somehow it's
similar to the way we don't like to look
at old people but prefer to look at
those who are
young if we don't want to look at Dua we
will never understand duka no matter how
many births we go through
Dua is a noble truth if we allow
ourselves to face it then we will start
to seek a way out of
it opposing our habits creates some
suffering generally we are afraid of
suffering if something will make us
suffer we don't want to do it well we
are interested in what appears to be
good and beautiful but we feel that
anything involving suffering is
bad it's not like that suffering is a
noble truth if there is suffering in the heart
truth if there is suffering in the heart
it be it's it becomes the cause that
makes you think about
escaping it leads you to contemplate you
won't sleep so soundly because you will
be intent on investigating to find out
what is really going on trying to see
the causes and the
results so the first thing he's saying
there is uh the first thing you you must
do you in order to free yourself from
suffering is
suffer if your attitude is all about
avoiding suffering the like the the
non-transparency we discussed
before uh then you can't free yourself
from suffering cu cu your only concern
is to not acknowledge the fa that you
suffer but then you also have the other
way of um suffering but then expecting
uh expecting your
um expecting things you do things You
observe uh um environment circumstances
your livelihood you expect those things
to sort out your
suffering so you need to suffer you need
to uh
recognize the uh well inevitability of
suffering but then you are the one who
must understand that who must make the
effort to understand the nature of it
cuz that's the only freedom from
suffering not like you just miraculously
get cured from suffering if you repent
long enough or if you if you endure the
the physical suffering mental suffering
long enough everything falls into place
no uring these this suffering that
arises on account of restraint and so on
yeah that is the first step but that in
itself will not result in sensation of
suffering if there was so that's that's
what the Buddha would have said so but
no it's the understanding of the
Suffering The arising the sensation and
so on that's what frees you from that
suffering and that's that's exactly what
is saying here if if you are only
concerned about avoiding suffering
maintaining attitude that suffering is
bad you are never going to uh well
acknowledge it acknowledge it as a as a
as a necessary basis for your Liberation
even even if you practice for Liberation
or you think you are uh you're not
practicing correctly cuz CU there is no
basis of suffering first that's what the
Buddha said as well um how do he put it
all I teach is suffering and freedom
from it so you realize that people first
need to learn how to suffer because the
most common attitude with suffering is
present is I must avoid this I must turn
away from this I must get rid of this or
okay I'll endure this because just going
through this suffering will will
miraculous result in the
Revelation so how how to suffer how to
recognize suffering not you don't need
to go seeking other the suffering cuz
you are already in the position of
suffering all you need to do is stop
distracting yourself from it um stop
ignoring it how like like how to suffer or how to
it how like like how to suffer or how to
recognize that you are already within
the domain of suffering well you do so
by by recognizing the fact that like
your own life your own health your own
youth um people around you your own
investment your own house your own
things you have imagine it being taken
away t night losing it and then see
genuinely contemplate that allow those
thoughts to arise to manifest themselves
and then see are you going to be
emotionally perturbed are you going to
be affected by it and that that didn't
already suffering so see you're not
actually suffering in a sense of you
lost everything you just think about it
and that's already suffering and that's
exactly how people avoid that suffering
but refusing to think about it oh you
must not think about it is
depressing and and that's exactly why
you can't liberate yourself from what
you're liable to cuz you stop you you're
refusing to acknowledge that you're
liable to
it and also the the whole everything
you're doing is maintaining you're
maintaining yourself maintaining your
family maintaining your job oh
absolutely yeah because if you stopy
maintain and then why are you
maintaining it because the the thought
the notion of not having it makes you
suffer yeah so you are on the Bas all
you doing is is trying to deal with
suffering uh that at the same time
you're denying it's affecting you no I
have nothing nothing bothers in my life
I'm happy okay well if if you don't do
anything tomorrow if there is no burden
on you to keep performing to keep
providing to keep doing to keep living
uh are you still going to remain
happy or are you going to start like
like drowning in boredom they then going
to become anxiety and Dread they will
overwhelm you and make it go
mad so so everything you do is in order
to avoid suffering including denial of
suffering you do it because you already
suffer you're just not Dr drowning in it
you're already drowning you are already
drowning you're not learning how to swim
across to the safe Shore so all you're
doing is learning how to
basically keep your mouth above the
water and you can sustain that only for
so long sooner or later you will Dr
that's why the would kept talking and
giving simuls of the the the crossing
the flood crossing the shore safety of
the other Shore and so
on cuz that is the only
safety so I continue with
the
talk happy people don't develop wisdom
they are asleep it's like a dog that
eats its full afterwards it doesn't want
to do anything it can sleep all day it
won't bark if a burglar comes it's too
full too tired but if you only give it a
little food it will be alert and awake
if someone tries to come sneaking around
it'll jump up and start
barking that's like what we spoke the
other day like the the Spartans the
ancient Spartan the Spartan children SP
intentionally like underfed so they're
always alert
yeah well that's see like happy people
that's exactly what he means by it is
what I was saying people who refuse to
acknowledge that even their happiness is
under the burden of
suffering by refusing to acknowledge it
you get to enjoy your happiness or so it
seems ignorance is bliss exactly yeah
but ignorance is bliss in the sense of
uh ignorance is never ignorance is an
act of ignoring it's as I said before
many times it's not a metaphysical lack
of information
or mystery it's actually your attitude
of ignoring which means deep down you
know what you're
ignoring that's why ignorance is
undoable if you make the effort to undo
the habit of ignoring certain truths
certain uh Natures of your existence
certain liabilities certain obviousness
of your of your experience and
existence and that's why ignorant
sensuality go hand in hand and
sensuality provides you this distraction
which is helps you uh distraction makes
your act of ignoring
effortless because distracts and
pleasure is at the end of this
distraction so me making the effort to
ignore what I deep down inside already
know it becomes much
easier so it's ignorance procrastination
all these things it sort of like
perpetuating that same attitude of
fundamental AA of not acknowledging
certain truths not refusing to look at
it pretending it's not there
or sometimes you can't pretend it's not
there but then you okay I'll deal with
it later oh everybody dies I'll deal
with it when my time comes and so
on but how do you think again even if
you stop and reflect wait a minute my
whole life is about avoiding this yet
here I am holding a magical belief that
suddenly when it comes after 50 60 years
on this Earth I'll be able to deal with
it yet while I while I could deal with
it I was refusing to deal with it cuz it
was tooo unpleasant so it's too
unpleasant to think about death when you
are alive and somehow you maintain a
notion that you'll be able to deal with
it when it's actually
occurring if it's unpleasant when to
think about it you can only imagine how
unpleasant it's going to be when it's
actually
there I'll continue
with if we speak the subtle dama most
people will be frightened by it they
they won't dare to enter it even saying
don't do evil most people can't follow
them that's how it is so I've sought all
kinds of means to get this across one
thing I I often say is no matter if we
are delighted or upset happy or
suffering shedding tears or singing
songs never mind living in this world we
are in a cage we don't get Beyond this
condition of being in a cage even if
you're rich if you're living in a cage
if you are poor you're living in a cage
you're burdened by the same liability to
suffering if you watch a movie you're
watching in a cage that's exactly what I
saying you have to realize that your
happiness watching a movie Family
successful business is within the burden
of
suffering you are caged by it that's
exactly that so it's not there's no
happiness everything is depressing no
there is but you have to look at the
bigger picture happiness or grief it's
within the burden of suffering it's
within the liability of
suffering and that's the
problem but you maintain the attitude of
ignoring that problem through taking
that happiness for granted which then
means you will be taking avoiding of any
grief and suffering for granted as
well what what is this cage it is the
cage of birth aging illness death
in this way we are imprisoned in the
world this is mine this is mine that
belongs to me we don't know what we
really are or what we are doing actually
actually we are all doing all we are
doing is accumulating suffering for
ourselves it's not something far away
that causes our suffering but we don't
look at ourselves however much happiness
and comfort we may have having been born
we cannot avoid aging we must fall ill
and we must die this is du itself Here
and Now H
liability of your
resistance like not there's absolutely
no alternative to that the only
alternative is to free yourself from it
or to ignore
it so this is some uh excerts from AA
damor it's
called it can be done
this is about halfway through the
through the
talk niana P
for one need not aim at anything or wish
for anything at all just aim for
Nana all manner of becoming in birth
Merit and virtue in the in the worldly
way do not reach
there making Merit and skillful CA
hoping it will cause us to attain to
some better
State we don't need to be wishing for a
lot of things just aim directly for
nuana wanting CA wanting Tranquility we
just end up in the same old place it's
not necessary to desire these things we
should just wish for the place of
sensation the most important point is
that while we have life we should train
the mind to be even in regard to things
we should be able to share wealth and
possessions when the time comes we
should give a portion to those in need
just as if we were giving things to our
own children sharing things like this we
will feel happy and we can give away all
our wealth then whenever our breath may
stop there will be no attachment or
anxiety because everything is
gone the Buddha taught to die before you
die to be finished with things before
they are finished then you can be at
ease let things break before they are broken
let things break before they are broken
let them finish before they before they
are
finished this is the Buddha's intention
in teaching the dammer even if you
listen to the teachings for 100 or
thousand eons if you do not understand
these points you won't be able to undo
your suffering and you will not find
peace you will not see the Dum but
understanding these things according to
the Buddha's intention and being able to
resolve things is called seeing the
things is called seeing the
Dumber this view of things can make an
end of suffering it it can relieve all
heat and
distress whoever strives sincerely and
is diligent in practice who can endure
who trains and develops himself to the
full measure those persons will attain
to peace and
sensation wherever they stay they will
have no suffering whether they are young
or old they will be free of suffering
whatever their situation whatever work
they have to perform they will have no
suffering because their minds have
reached the place where suffering is
exhausted where there is
peace so it's it's the teaching is
simply aim at
nibana go for
it yeah try to understand what that is
yeah exactly in order in order to aim at
something you need to know what it is so
I was going to say but I decided to let
you finish the bit where it
says like you you you want
it means you you must know at least
where to look for it you must have some
understanding and that's the problem for
most people especially when they start
the practice you kind
of well you start with like non
understanding of fana is of course but
you continue like you st making efforts but
continue like you st making efforts but
none of those efforts are actually aimed
at clarifying like no hold on let me get
the idea at least what niana is cuz
through getting the idea you get to know
what it is and what you can do about it
but for most people they expect nibana
to
happen on account of you know their
commitment to the meditation technique
or something they expect Nana to occur
and then all my problems will be will be
gone but niban is about undoing things
that make you liable to problems they
make you liable to
suffering nibana is not just a
replacement just a new novelty
experience that replaces everything
overrides everything else nibana is the
experience uh in the sense of when you
undone when you have undone all the UNH
wholesome all your desire all your ill
will all your um attitude of of
distraction and
delusion that negative experience that's
left as a result of that undoing that's
what Meb is that is also a d a phenomena
but it's a d it's undetermined by any
GRE version of
delusion so people will be better off
when they start practicing to think to
to spend their time thinking about dhama
then practicing their mindfulness of
sorry think about dham and Iana then
practice their mindfulness of breathing
or something which going to be some
mechanical physical
technique you reflect on so what is what
is the Buddha sayana is it's a ation
and from a point of view of somebody who
started a practice what is the other
thing that you could say it's a
sensation it's death so is niana closer
based on the Buddhist description to
what you have the idea that death is or
is it closer to some kind of
transcendental astral projection realm
of your
Liberation no it's closer to death
actually cuz nibana is against the grain
of Life what's the other thing that's
against the grain of life it's death and
that's why people would freak out in the
sutas when they would understand nibana
and the Buddha would teach and it was oh
well that will kill me that will destroy
me and they Despair and start pulling
their hair and so on like full on
existential dread cuz you realize oh no that's what
dread cuz you realize oh no that's what
and the only reason you fear death fear
nibana is because you refuse to give up
um your possession of your life that's
it you don't have to give up your life
as in you don't have to go and kill
yourself to 10 that's nonsense but you
must give away the possession of your
life which for most people equates death
which is why it's so frightening die
before you die and that's what said yeah
die before you die and that's exactly
what it means nibana is closer to the
death for pujan from PJ's point of view
than anything else is hence the Buddha
himself was teaching marati as the
quickest sharpest way for enlightenment
contemplation of death yeah it's a bit
too sharp for some
people so he mellowed it out a bit but
fundamentally that's exactly why it it
so it directly results in in in in
Liberation if you do it rightly because
it's right that's also why like um it
said which is you know I know people
mystified but it's you know the in the sutas where
but it's you know the in the sutas where
it said like um somebody develops the
Right View but they haven't reached the
fruits of it yet they don't do it they
do it at the moment of the death and so
on and it's almost like a mystical
always in moment of the death you get
this light Revelation no you you you
reach the fruits of your right view for
example or your arship at the moment of
your death because that's when niana is
so your right view has already
understood it whatever been preventing
you maybe you were not as as diligent as
you should have been but once you're
going through the experience of dying
what you're going to have with yourself
there is only your right view or wrong
view so if you haven't developed the
Right View during life that's why yeah
when death comes it's too late to do
anything about it but you like you say
your view is there for you that's all
you have there exactly so when your
right view is there that's why oh he
gets his Enlightenment or becomes an
Aran at the moment of dying as in when
he's dying cuz that's what Nana is for a
living mind
sensation sensation of AG but now he's
there with the Right View not with a
VI and that's the difference and it
would be different for him because he
made the effort while he was still alive
he died before he
died you you fully remove any
possessiveness any like make sure
everything ceases in the sense of not
you go around destroying things but you
destroy your emotional dependence upon
things including your own life your own
health your own youth your own family
everything everything everything why
because you emulate death when death
comes I can't even conceive a second
longer holding on to these things so we
Al I must no you don't have to destroy
the things just fully develop that theme
of being unable to hold on to this if he
decides to go
away because if destruction of things if
throwing away your possessions frees you
from possessions then as I said all you
have to do is take away this life to get
nibana but it doesn't work like that
doesn't it quite the opposite you need
this life in order to understand Iana so
you might be throwing away your
possessions to simplify your life to an
extent but if you think that throwing
away your possessions is bringing you
closer to nibana while you're seriously
deluded still you realize possessions are not
still you realize possessions are not
your possession is not in things it's
your attitude towards the things and
that's something you can't throw
away that's why the ultimate possession
of the views and the wrong views or the
right views your possession is not
things exactly exactly so you will die
before you die means you make sure you
have removed any appropriation any sense
of ownership in regard to your
experience as a whole whatever the
content of that experience is then when
the experience of death comes well
there's nothing there that contradicts
it there is no Assumption of possession
appropriation control that will be
directly at odds with the experience of
death which denies it so you're at peace
even in death hence it's not your death
you not being want destroyed by that
death cuz you're not there to be
destroyed or like what say be finished
before it's finished also say yeah yeah
yeah yeah sure sure exactly yeah yeah
they finish with things before they are
finished because they are going to be
finished for sure that's up forand who
is finished who is inana death is
partana it's not even death and the
Buddha wouldn't even use the word death
for an Arun he would say the Aggregates
break apart he wouldn't use the same po
word for it but for PJ yeah he dies so
you realize you don't die because your
Aggregates break apart you die because
the Aggregates break apart that you are
appropriating them that's why you die
you're appropriating them and they break
apart so there is death so that's why
like arahant cannot
prevent um five Aggregates from breaking
apart cannot prevent body from from from
withering away and
dying so if that's truly what death is
as in the mere destruction of the body
then nobody can be free from that but it
it isn't it's the appropriation of that
which will be destructed destroyed by
the by the death or or an accident or
old age or
sickness that appropriation makes it
death aging and and sickness and so on
without it it
isn't it's just a falling apart it's
just you can designate whichever way you
want my cup has died yeah it's just
basically change sensation of this
something else but if there is no
appropriate creation means none of it
will be yours which means you done in
regard to the five
Aggregates but the problem is this is
obviously much subtler harder thing to
see and it's much easier to just either
deny your life deny your possessions
throw everything away burn your house
must not own anything must not help
anyone cuz everything is
attachment your mind is the attachment
not things you get attached
to so you change your mind of being from
being mind of attachment to mind of
non-attachment everything else can stay
the same except of course the basic
virtue that needs to be done so yeah
certain amount of Engagement with the
with the with the world in an UNH
wholesome sense must be restrained but
then everything else yeah I mean the
Buddha himself would have stayed in the
king's palaces and whatnot and if that's
how you measure the attachment means he
was extremely attached but that's
ridiculous thing to say
now that doesn't mean oh so I can go and
stay in the Palaces well are you the
Buddha are you an arant if not well you
have to be careful you careful in a
sense you have to see what is it that
makes it wholesome or UNH wholesome what
is it that makes it it doesn't matter if
I stay in King's Palace or what is it
that matters as in I'm becoming attached
to staying in King's Palace are you
aware of that if you are then yeah you
probably won't be affected wherever you
stay you'll be at EAS as I says by
things coming going heav losing doesn't
matter your mind becomes even exactly
even yeah so yeah so
nibana
being non- greed non-h hatred non
delusion so we can develop this exactly
every day every day all time through
clarifying what greed what desire for
sensual pleasures and so on is
you get to discern what non- greed is so
if I'm if I'm greeing greedy for
something I I can acknowledge that and
not engage with it yeah so first your
body needs to be restrained you're not
habitually just giving into it even
before you recognize the thought being
present intention towards those things
present once you're physically
restrained then yeah you can start
noticing it on the level of your mind
and then you realize okay these thoughts
have arason on their own but I'm not
obliged to say yes to the desire that
has arisen I don't have to try and get
rid of it because it wasn't my doing in
the first place I didn't create this
desire in my mind has arisen it
manifested but I can certainly I am
certainly responsible if I choose to
welcome it if I choose to entertain it
if I choose to think further upon it
same with ill will same with
distraction so that's why I mean it's
better of than rather than like sitting
and trying to get experience from
meditation sit quietly and make him
ation about experience of understanding
what these things are cuz that's where
the peace is when you're not affected by
your thoughts changing when you're not
affected by the desire arising or or
disagreeable displeasure arising or
boredom arising it doesn't affect you
means you don't have to act out of it if
you don't act out of it you stop
perpetuating the very things that
prevent you from experiencing the B
great diversion
delusion and so if you do that for one
hour yeah you do that for one hour but
it wasn't the hour of kind of mindless
sort of head
noding flawed meditation flawed
meditation as we said before it's an
hour of of of of clarifying the meaning
of these mental states which means even
when you're not in your meditation then
when you go by your life the back of
your mind those themes are still going
to be present so that's how you start to
meditate regardless of your posture cuz
it's not I'm meditating I'm meditating
it's just developing the theme establish
your mind Liv upon the perception of the
non- greed non aversion non delusion
perception of renunciation all those
meditations that the Buddha talks about
in the sutas are basically themes upon
which you can establish your mind if you
spend long enough time dwelling on
it that's what would would say his mind
turns towards it inclines he doesn't
turn towards company cuz what cuz he's
been thinking about this that's why he
starts to Value because he values it he
establishes himself upon it because of
that nothing inferior to those states
can disturb
you I like it the theme the theme of
Nana making your l oh Nana is just like
wow it's so why is it
unattainable absence of greed diversion
delusion that's what is so just start
looking at how much how much percentage
of your daily life you spend cultivating
desire welcoming it being careless about
it ill will uh distraction oh I'm bored
I'm going to do this I'm going to read
this I'm going to watch that I'm going
to go and talk to these people and you
really no if I were to stop doing these
things rooted in desire rooted in ill
will rooted in delusion and
distraction that's that brings me closer
to nibana that's a direct that's closer
to what nibana is than anything else I
do on top of these things yeah even if
it's going to become a monk for 60 years
and whatnot
if you do that on top of your G
diversion delusion you're not a step
closer to
niana and just by doing that refraining
from those un wholesome things then it
doesn't really matter what your life
will form around it you know what I mean
whether you become a monk or not that's
not the point yeah that's not the
exactly but things will s to form around
your life you will go hang around
monasteries Maybe might become well you
might not hang around depending on the
monastery I guess uh but uh yeah the
point is you your mind will be then
inclining towards things that the Buddha
was describing as the mind will be
inclining to seclusion non- company U
renunciation release finding basically
joy in that Solitude in that
non-engagement not because you're afraid
of Engagement or you know how to deal
with it no it's because you're you're
you're contemplating the theme of niana
which naturally results in this so then
when engage engagement comes it won't
bother you but you will certainly not
try to make it stay longer because
you're actually bored on your own no
quite the
contrary you do it as a sense of Duty I
have no problem with that but you won't
be doing it a second longer for any
other reason that's what would meant
says when the when the like a monk whose
mind is inclined towards Nana seclusion
practice when he's visited by Kings and
retinues and other people he would just
say enough to answer the questions but
not a word longer to make make them kind
of linger or stay just yeah you don't
want them there basically you don't want
anyone anywhere around you cuz that's
the whole point seclusion kind of ties
in with that whole idea of cation and
renunciation but that doesn't mean that
automatically just by locking yourself
alone in the room you're suddenly
practicing seclusion of nibana no it's
seclusion of greed seclusion from your
own mind of greed a verion delusion that
then gets sort of uh exemplified with
also physical seclusion and all these
other things so physical seclusion can
help you but don't mistake that to be
like this seclusion that results in
liberation of your mind well one thing
for sure company will not help either
way unless it's a company of somebody
with the right viewer higher but then in
that case they wouldn't want to have you
near them why would they associate with
PJ you's got to be honest with yourself
is this is this uh causing more greed
more ex why why am I going for this now
is it because I'm just trying to like
get away from stuff what's
stuff is the stuff I'm trying to get
away un wholesome okay if it's UNH
wholesome it's fine just want to get
away but if it's not UNH wholesome then
why am I trying to get away from it why
am I bothered by it you have to realize
that the responsibility for your own
suffering is only on you
which means responsibility from
liberation of your own suffering will be
also on you circumstances do not make
you suffer it's your own attitude in
regard to circumstances that makes you
suffer so this is another well there
still from that talk it can be done I
can CH a few more excerpts this is from the
CH a few more excerpts this is from the
beginning of the
talk when it comes to taking precepts
for example a monk will proclaim the
precept and the lay people will vow to
undertake them don't misunderstand what
is going on the truth is that morality
is not something that can be given it
can't really be requested or received
from someone we can't give it to someone
else in our vacular we hear people say
the renable monk gave the precepts and
we received the
precepts we talk like this here in the
countryside and so it has become our
habitual way of understanding if we
think like like like
this that we come to receive precepts
from the monks or on the lunar
observance days and then if the monkss
won't give the precepts then we don't
have morality that is only a tradition
of delusion that that we have inherited
from our
ancestors thinking in this way means
that we give up our own responsibility
not having firm trust and conviction in
ourselves then it gets passed down to
the Next Generation and they too come to
to receive precepts from the monk to
receive precepts from the mon and the
monks come to believe that they are the
ones who give the precepts to the
ly in fact morality and precepts are not
like that they're not something to be
given or
received in truth morality resides with
the intentions of people if we have the
conscious determination to refrain from
harmful activities and wrongdoing by way
of body speech
then morality is coming about within you
you should know it within
yourself it is okay to take the vows
with another person you can also
recollect the precepts by yourself if
you don't know what they are then you
can request them from someone else it's
not something very complicated or
distant so really whenever we wish to
receive morality and Dumber we have them
right here and now it is just like the
air that surrounds us everywhere
whenever we breathe we take it in all
manner of Good and Evil is like that if
we wish to do good we can do it anywhere
at any time we can do it alone or
together with others evil is the same we
can do it with a large or small group in
a hidden or open
place well that's kind of self
self-explanatory really it's it's again it's about don't
really it's it's again it's about don't
project responsibility for your own
virtue and morality
on the external form that you can use to
to learn from or to remind you of it but
ultimately it's on
you so like if you haven't had the
chance to formally take the precepts in
the monastery it's it's simply completely
monastery it's it's simply completely
unrelatable to whether you keep the
precepts or not you the one making the
magical connection I can't be moral now
cuz I haven't recited it in front of a
monk no you recite it to remind yourself
what you should be doing whether you
recite or not which is keep the
precepts five precepts is what what
would have said distinguishes humans
from animals oh continue a little bit
there cuz what you just said
now says morality this is something that
we should consider normal for all humans
to practice yeah exactly a person who
has no morality is no different from an
animal if you decide to live like an
animal then of course there is no good
or evil for you because an an animal
doesn't have any knowledge of such
things a c catches mice but we don't say
it is doing evil because it has no
concept of knowledge of good or bad
right or
wrong these beings are outside the
circle of human beings it is the animal
realm the Buddha pointed out that this
group is just living according to the
animal kind of actions those who
understand right and wrong good and evil
are humans Buddha taught he's Dumber for
humans Buddha taught he's Dumber for
humans if we if we people don't have
morality and knowledge of these things
then we are not much different from
animals so it is appropriate that
appropriate that we study and learn
about them and and make ourselves able
this is taking advantage of the precious
accomplishments of human existence and
bringing it to
fulfillment yeah so as as we said just a
few minutes ago it's nothing I mean you
you might have to do it initially learn
about it take that kind of formal sense
but you recognize it's a about your
day-to-day life um it's about what goes on in your
life um it's about what goes on in your
mind throughout day-to-day life so watch
your mind okay yeah that's good but
watch your mind for
what watch your mind for un holesome
okay so you see a wholesome so what do
you do about it you try to get rid of it
the level of your mind but that kind of
implies you're in in control of your
mind you're in control of what arises in
your mind you have saying it but do you
not Accord to the Buddha where by mind
and the thoughts is just another sense
mind wants to think eyes want to see so
that's not on you so then you realize
okay so what is on me then when thoughts
of Desire or thoughts of ill will
present themselves what is on me where
is the line there up to which I'm
responsible before or after
which am I not
be so all these Reflections is something
people don't don't usually do you just
want to be told what to do told where to
focus told what to read if anything and
things will fall into place no there is
no falling into place it's you building
a place and then putting things there
literally manly effort manly strength
manly determination as suas would often
determination as suas would often
describe it so you ask yourself
throughout your day life okay
so is my mind affected by desire now are
the things that I'm maybe I don't want
right now but I I think about something
I want later why do I want it what is it
is it for my benefit for benefit of
others whose benefit what's the result
of it is it genuine benefit to to my
livelihood to my health or is it just a
distraction and
pleasure now some can be mixed so you
look further okay so it's it's for my
health but it also are there
alternatives for my health that will not
necessarily be as pleasant yes there are
um would I be affected if say I go for
those alternatives but I don't go for
the Alternatives of pleasure that I want
so in other words you ask yourself will
I be emotionally disturbed if I don't
get the pleasure I want if so you don't
go for that pleasure then there and then
next time you might not be disturbed but
you have to be honest with yourself and
transparent so that these questions can
start to
apply and that's why I keep saying like
don't necessarily rush to give the
answer because it's not about the answer
it's about becoming a question yourself
cuz that's how you start to question
your own existential attitude you know
like the expression like oh let that
sink in like don't rush just let it sink
in that's exactly what you're doing you
you bring out the theme through a
question but you don't rush answering it
just let it endure even for a day or two
let it be on your mind that's a theme
you're developing for a day or two
that's already a form of Sam it's
sinking in that particular thing you're
reflecting why why do I prefer
this over that why do I fear this why is
this a
problem either way it all comes down to
am I
emotionally affected by these
things am I does does this pleasure
emotionally make me angry make me lash
out does pleasure emotionally make me
cray for it make me go for sensuality
does neutral feeling emotionally make me
sort of just turn to Oblivion and
distraction if so you you don't
cultivate that but it doesn't mean you
try to get rid of everything and stop
everything so you recognize
responsibility is not for the thoughts
that have a Ison responsibili for acting
out of it for welcoming it as I said
before for entertaining it as the Buddha
described so many times so that's what
you do but many people would think okay
so I must not I must stop thinking this
I must not think this I have thoughts of
sensuality I must stop thinking that
yeah you must stop indulging that but
you must also stop trying to get rid of
it in a sense of that you are the master
controller of it in the first place cuz
that becomes your form of Engagement
with it trying to negate it that's why
you remain bound to it cuz it wasn't
your doing the arising of those thoughts
but in order to arrive at the point
where you can start seeing those
thoughts in your mind like that you must
have you must develop virtue and like
restrain your physical actions and your
speech which means you must toughen up
basically through that restraint and
renunciation you must develop some
standards that you're able to withhold
the pain with withhold discomfort
without acting out of it right away
because sensuality is
uncomfortable that's why that's why it's
so it's so so
enchanting cuz not just that you avoid
the initial hit of discomfort of not
getting the sensuality you want but down
the line provides you with pleasure on
top of it so it feels like win-win but
it isn't isn't it cuz fundamentally you
still act out of trying to avoid a pain
ill will is uncomfortable if you're not
able to hold it without acting without
saying something how can you then see
your thoughts being entertained in
regard to it you
can't so that's what I mean you need to
toughen up by toughening up you develop
up by toughening up you develop
confidence that you know you won't be
acting out of it which means you leave
yourself no other choice but to deal
with the suffering that you have trapped
and enclosed within yourself and that's
the first bits of the the first talk you
read from today was that you must learn
how to suffer and then you'll know what
to do or how to do about suffering how
to go about
suffering so throughout the day just
keep reflecting keep asking yourself
you're engag in certain actions right
here right now okay why am I doing this
where is this
rooted I'm not sure okay let that
question then endure there a bit
more is this sensal ill will
carelessness what is it what would
happen if I suddenly this stops like
whatever I'm doing it taken away will I
be flustered will I be affected doesn't
mean you have to go and destroy it but
means you always have to be aware of
what effect might have on you that's how
you get to learn from
it I'll read a a short verse my I think
it's related uhhuh in terms of striving
and you're saying toughen up right you
need to tough up that's from the
terata 3.5 by a disciple of the Buddha named
3.5 by a disciple of the Buddha named
matanga the son of
matanga so he's
verse this it's too cold too hot too
late they say when the young neglect
their work like this opportunities pass
them by but one who considers hot and
cold old as nothing more than Blades of
grass he does his manly Duty and his
happiness never fails exactly with my
chest with my chest I'll thrust aside
the grasses Vines and creepers and
Foster seclusion
yeah no we spoke about it many times
before you know modern world especially
Western World I don't think AG is too
different but he yeah everything
everything is wanted on easy terms
everything is wanted on my own
terms and then people think oh they had
all the luck being born in the time of
the Buddha yeah there was a bit of luck
but they were never too hungry tooold
that's not why they were lucky they were
lucky because the circumstances were
harder were optimal as the Buddha would
say not harder in a sense they were
tortured but hard in a sense they could
have not be existentially
spoiled take things for granted
sensuality proliferated left and right
it was just
impossible that's why they were lucky
that's why the time was
optimal cuz they were kept in check by
circumstances the mind could not have
proliferated which means it wasn't as
polluted as the mines today are on
average and that's the difference so
today in order for people to understand
they need to do much more self- induced
pollution that they've been C acting
throughout their life through education
relationship everything else you just
keep adding to
it and that's the difference and and
that and and and you could also see like
just from the point of view of that like
toughen up in mental toughness or being
able to withhold the
pain on average how much softer we are
today much much
softer I mean back in the day you know
like you lose your whole
family in the flood six of your eight
children
die you know you go
on but today it's just like not being
able to have a child you need 20 years
of
counseling well not to have dinner you
need 20 years oh yeah yeah you don't get
enough food yeah dinner you get enough
breakfast and lunch sorry yeah no
actually nobody like in southern in the
western world everybody gets enough food
it's most people get enough food but
it's more
like not as much as you used to or
something like that no those are the
little things that's what I mean like
you start reflecting like why am I
frightened in the prospect of this I
remember when I when I started reading
the the sutas and then the okay
renunciation and precept I I want to do
the fasting but not fasting even like
I'll never eat or something I just I'll
skip a dinner today and I get this like
anxiety oh I'll go to bed hungry I mean
I was only about 16 17 but still I'm
thinking you're not going to die you ate
twice that day maybe even more more I
don't even remember I just decide to
skip the habit of
dinner and it my mind was freaking out
fortunately for me with my own views at
the time I saw that as a challenge that
I must overcome many people would not
necessarily think that they would think
okay no I'll just go and eat I shouldn't
be doing
this but the fact that you will get so
frightened just by not shoving enough
not shoving the same amount of food in
your mouth which is more than enough
even what you already ate for sustenance
um macronutrients everything is already
covered yet you're still freaking out
for not eating what you're used to
that's what I mean you're existentially
spoiled like the threshold of what you
deem is necessary is far too inflated
than what actually is necessary so
that's why yes circumstances simpli
simplification of many things in today
Modern Life is it's more likely going to
result in good than in bad even if they
don't take it further in terms of
practice Dharma and everything else it's
certainly going to prevent uh depression
and all sorts of modern ailments that
kind of plague the Western
World cuz everything bothers you cuz
you're too soft that's why the the the
guidelines the precepts they're there
you can find them easily absolutely yeah
just take those on and it's been around
even after you know not necessarily like
in stoicism and all these other it was
the same people realize that if you
start to to like practice the degree of
self-restraint you develop certain
strength that that the whole apathy the
word apathy from AP the Greek I think
it's Greek Latin Greek um literally
means means indifferent means equanimous
means even in regard to anything that
comes your
way now of course there is the ultimate
evenness of arship but even the relative
eveness is a good place to start or
something to strive for there were those
sutas where the Buddha described those
the two kingdoms and says why this
Kingdom will always win is because they
sleep on wooden pillows they bath in
cold water they're like they wake up
before the sun wake up before the sun
yeah yeah yeah they always Vigilant live
on that kind of physical hardship to a
degree which keeps them sharp it's so
see pujan cannot necessarily decide oh
make myself wise or I prevent myself
from proliferating but putuj can
certainly recognize that circumstances
can play the part in his mind
proliferating toward sensuality or real
will so then he prevents the
circumstances from spoiling
him and that's what those kingdoms that
would always win do those were the
values that they
cherished yeah you put them in the
environment of getting after the sun
bathing with soft nice scented warm
water they will go the same way human
mind is the human mind Universal nature
is the same but you recognize the
circumstances so you prevent yourself
from ending up in that way as in you
take responsibility for
it oh it's not my fault that soft that
warm water makes me soft it's not my
fault that soft pillow makes me makes me
lazy in the morning well it
is yeah it's not your fault that
softness of your pillow results in
softness of your body but it's your
fault to choose that that will then
result in the softness of your body and
being unable to Bear the
elements most that a lot of people don't
even know about these things nowadays no
you know it's like it's but see it's not
exactly like I remember that's what I'm
saying like when I started I wasn't even
necessarily just directly naming sutas
and it was the very early the first like
days of reading anything like meditation
and uh philosophy and spiritual things
the most the first conclusion it's it
it's like oh
self-restraint I can't be smoking
drinking going around partying and
expect like to develop mental no you you
have like it was just the most natural
immediate conclusion which I think many
people have at the back of their mind
but they might you know go at Great
length to cover it up and then try to
sort of twist and bend and have it all
you know you can be a lay man enjoy
enjoy sensuality and everything and
being an Arun at the same
time wish you all the best with that